Strong sense of self creates difficulties
in relationships with others.
I have a strong sense of self.
So, when I see a person
who takes advantage of others,
I am unable to withhold my feelings,
I lash out at them with foul languages.
(Audience Laughter)
I am unable to control the swearing words
coming out of my mouth.
Unfortunately, I met such
an undesirable character at work.
He bothered me a lot so I had
a great deal of conflict with him.
As I was experiencing the conflict,
I also thought that I, too,
could have some problems.
Instead of loving myself,
if someone causes me a bit of harm,
I am not able to forgive and I demand
the justice due from him.
Of course, I do not treat
everyone this harshly.
Only those who go beyond
the code of ethics that I have.
For example, the guy
at work was such a case.
Though he apologized and
asked for forgiveness,
he would turn around and back stabbed me.
He was such a person who would ask
for pardon but cheated behind my back.
(Questioner) Having had a few
rows of conflict with him
and others in a similar way,
I began to think that I am the one
who is unable to love myself,
and unable to get along with others.
So, I did 108 prostrations and
studied Buddhist Sutras.
Still, those painful memories
resurface and linger on.
(Questioner) It has become painful
for me to relate others in general now.
So, I would like to ask you how
I can have more self-confidence,
and deal with conflicts
with better outcome.
Yes.
I will say very frankly,
that you have a bad personality.
Not a strong sense of self,
but an undesirable personality.
If you keep this up, you will have
a nervous breakdown eventually.
It will destroy you.
You don't have a strong sense of self;
you are too obsessed with
your own opinions.
This is different from having
a strong sense of self.
You need to give up your own thoughts
and opinions in order to have
a strong sense of self.
If you let go of your own views,
you become free from what others do.
You are not bothered by
what others say or do.
That is what a person with
strong sense of self does.
He is not influenced by what other do.
You may think that right and wrong,
good and evil are clear,
but those are just your opinions.
Those are born out of your own world view.
So, the guy at work is not the problem.
The problem is within you.
If you look at it as his problem,
you are the one getting hurt.
You should look at yourself.
It is wrong to think that
the problem lies with him.
If you think this way, no amount
of Sutra study will help you.
What is the central teaching of the Sutras?
It is the Emptiness doctrine.
Everything is empty.
Nothing is inherently right or wrong
Nothing is inherently correct or incorrect,
because everything is empty.
Nothing is inherently good or evil.
Nothing is inherently clean or dirty.
These are the teachings of the Sutras.
You ought to understand this.
You read the sutras but you maintain
your strong judgemental thoughts.
Those views have nothing to do
with Buddha's teaching.
So, if nothing is inherently right or
wrong, what has he done that is so bad?
That he backstabbed me,
He did wrong to me, these are
all but you own opinions.
He is living his life according
to his point of view.
You just don't like his ways.
You have different
value systems to live by.
So, accepting him as he is,
this is how you love yourself.
If you accept him as he is,
you are free from whatever he does.
You think he apologized to you,
but in fact, you are beholden to him.
Because your well-being is
dependent on how he behaves.
So, you are being servile to him.
You are not better than him.
You are behaving as his servant.
If you accept him as he is, you are fine,
regardless of how he conducts his life.
Even though you work at the same place,
he lives his life, you live yours.
You don't need to bother with him.
If you don't bother, you are free.
But, you are now enslaved by him.
You are suffering because of him.
Why do you suffer because of his problems?
This is a foolish way of living.
How old are you?
(Questioner) I am 35 years old.
Are you married?
(Questioner) No.
No?
With that kind of personality,
it's a good thing that you are not.
You wouldn't be able to live with
a wife with that kind of outlook.
Even when you're married, your wife
has her own life and you have your own.
Since you come different backgrounds,
the value systems, tastes in food,
hobbies, preferences, moral and
ethical standards are all different.
But if you were to judge something
according to your standards only,
how can you live with another person?
So, you must give up judging others
according to your own standard.
You can live if you give those up.
Because you are so tied
to your views, you're feeling ill.
Then you'd have to go to a hospital.
From now on, understand others
from their point of views.
"I can see how he would look
at it that way, " for example.
Are you working?
(Questioner) No, since I quit my job,
I am preparing to do something else.
You will have hard time
with other things, too.
You need to take care
of this problem first.
Have you attended
the enlightenment workshop?
(Questioner) No, I have not.
Then, do that first.
Before you get started on other work.
Attend that workshop and
learn to give up your views.
You need to examine yourself first.
You need to be able to drop your
anger and rage within yourself first.
Then, you will be able to start with
new work and to get along with people.
You can be a good supervisor
to the subordinates well,
and you will be able
to respect the higher ups, too.
You will be able to be a trustworthy friend
and will have meaningful relationships.
You need to let go of your ego.
That is the first thing.
You can't go on with your personality.
You say you want to love yourself,
but your personality will ruin your life.
I am glad you came today.
Take this opportunity to examine yourself
by attending the enlightenment
workshop soon.
Then, get started on the new work.
And do a lot of prostrations.
Whenever you have a chance,
do the bowings and pray, "You
are right. I am the one who is lacking."
Always bow with these thoughts.
But normally, you always
think you are right.
That is why you ought to recite, "
you are right; I am lacking."
You have to change your karma:
your old habit patterns.
You are a good looking man but you
suffer because of your old habits.
You shouldn't suffer, right?
You ought to live happily.
You can change your destiny.
(Sunim) If you keep this up,
you'll end up badly.
So, be resolute and change your old habits.
First, you must attend the workshop.
It is difficult to change by yourself.
Listening to me once
like this is not enough.
So, attend the workshop and
examine yourself deeply.
You will be able to examine
more objectively
(Sunim) when you're around
your fellow practitioners.
(Questioner) Thank you.
OK.
(Applause)